[SPEAKER_01]: On February 19, 1974, I'm talking to Mickey Vernon and going to ask him some questions about his career.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wonder if you'd start in by just briefly reviewing when you broke in, what your feelings were about playing first in the minor leagues and then making it to the big time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Doctor, I broke in in 1937 after
[SPEAKER_00]: completing a year of Villanova College.
[SPEAKER_00]: The team at Eastern Maryland was coached or managed by the Villanova coach, a fellow by the name of Doc Jacobs.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was also part owner of the franchise along with a fellow by the name of Duke Landgraf from Allentown, Pennsylvania.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are the ones that got me started in the pro ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was at Villanova on a baseball scholarship
[SPEAKER_00]: And I had come from a vocational high school and I really wasn't prepared for college, and so after the first year of college I dropped out and got into professional baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: And from there it just went, you know, to B-ball and then A-ball and then to the big leagues.
[SPEAKER_01]: This Doc Jacobs was your college coach and yet the
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, he was a varsity baseball coach at Villanova and he also coached and managed the Class D club in the Eastern Shore League.
[SPEAKER_00]: This was in 1937.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I joined his club in June and played about 85 games.
[SPEAKER_00]: They played 100 game schedules so I missed the first 15 or so games of that season.
[SPEAKER_00]: recall any records back in that year, they had a team at Salisbury, Maryland that had 25 games taken away from them on account of a couple of ineligible players.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on the last day of the season, Labor Day, we played the Salisbury team a doubleheader and they beat us a doubleheader and won the pennant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can imagine what kind of club they had.
[SPEAKER_00]: that they lost 25 games in the standings and still come back and won the pennant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why were the players ineligible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, at that time you were only allowed so many classmen on a Class D club.
[SPEAKER_00]: A classman is considered a fellow that's played a little pro ball.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody else had to be rookies.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were allowed five, I think, classmen and they had about seven or eight classmen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did any of those players make it big on that team you recall?
[SPEAKER_00]: A few of them made the big legs.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was a catcher by the name of Mike Guerra, a Cuban, that played for Philadelphia A's in Washington.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a fellow by the name of Kamelis, a pitcher, he made it with the Cubs.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a couple of fellas played in as high as Triple-A, but they were the only ones who made it to the big leagues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then from Easton to Greenville.
[SPEAKER_00]: To Greenville, South Carolina, in the old Sally League.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was Class B League then.
[SPEAKER_00]: I played one year there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was your manager at Greenville?
[SPEAKER_00]: A fellow named Jiggs Donahue.
[SPEAKER_01]: An old-timer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, he was.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the following year I went to Springfield, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was the Eastern League.
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you the property of any Major League team during these minor league years?
[SPEAKER_01]: Were these foreign teams for Washington?
[SPEAKER_00]: That brings up an interesting story because
[SPEAKER_00]: Doc Jacobs took me into Philadelphia to work out with the St. Louis Browns when they came to play the A's, and so they were going to have a working agreement with the St. Louis Browns, this Easton club.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I signed with them, and this was I think before the big bonuses came into being, and they promised me X number of dollars if they picked up my option at the end of the season.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Bill DeWitt, who later owned the club, came to Easton to look over the ballplayers, and he didn't pick up anyone's option.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Doc Jacobs sold me to Joe Cambria, who had the Salisbury Club in the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Cambria was a scout for Washington at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the following year, I was in the Washington organization.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the first year, I could have been in the St. Louis Browns organization.
[SPEAKER_00]: But my second year in pro ball, then I became property of the Washington Ball Club.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did things go at Springfield?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty good.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had a pretty good ball club.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jimmy Bloodworth was on the club and we were leading the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: On July 8th, I was leading the league in hitting and I was called up to Washington.
[SPEAKER_00]: I joined the club in Philadelphia on July 8th of 39.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I played the rest of the season with the Washington club.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the following season, they sent me back to Jersey City for another year, which I think was the best thing that could have happened to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even though I was hitting good in an A league, when they took me up to Washington, I was really outclassed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was in over my head.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I ended up hitting the, I was hitting 340 something at Springfield and I ended up hitting 250 something at Washington the last half of the season.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then that following year in AAA ball, Jersey City, the International League, really, you know, helped me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you have won the Eastern League title, do you think, if you had stayed there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you pretty far ahead?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think I had a good chance to, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course you were happy to get up though.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did you feel about that July 8th?
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally I was glad to be going to the big leagues and to join the club in Philadelphia, which was about 15 miles from my hometown, even made it more exciting.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't call anyone to tell them, I just wanted them to hear it on the radio or see it in the paper the next morning that I was in the lineup.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did you do that first game?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I joined the club, they were playing a doubleheader, and I arrived at the ballpark about the seventh inning of the first game.
[SPEAKER_00]: I came by train from Springfield to Philadelphia, and by the time I got out to the ballpark, it was the seventh inning of the first game, and I had a tough time getting in the park.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had to call the traveling secretary of the club to come down to the gate to
[SPEAKER_00]: to identify me and get me in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I dressed and I made my debut as a pinch runner in the ninth inning of the first game.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the second game I played the whole game and had one for four.
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the pitcher was a fellow named Beckman for the Philadelphia club.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you go home that night?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I did.
[SPEAKER_00]: I went back to Marcus Hook and saw my folks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was your manager at Springfield?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was that Bloodworth?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, Bloodworth was a player.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went to the big leagues and played a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: The manager was an old fellow that managed a long, long time in the minor leagues by the name of Spencer Abbott.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was a character.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was, you know, in baseball, and they have a lot of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at that time he had managed up until then all over the minor leagues, out in the Coast League for a few years.
[SPEAKER_00]: They told a story about him when he managed at Portland, Oregon.
[SPEAKER_00]: He threw up a bag of baseballs and come down and hit him on the head.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he jumped up in the dugout and hit his head on the dugout roof and knocked himself out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the players just let him lay there after the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't even take him into the clubhouse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was the manager at Washington when you came up in 39?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bucky Harris.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK. Now, how did they tell you you were going back to Jersey City?
[SPEAKER_01]: Was that at the end of the season or during the winter?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the spring training of 1940, I was with the Washington Club in Orlando up until the day before they broke camp to head north.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Mr. Griffith called me aside out the field that morning and said, we're going to send you to Jersey City on option, 24-hour recall.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said they're training over at Winter Haven.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said you can catch a bus and go over there and join their club.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the way they told me.
[SPEAKER_01]: What was he like, the old fox?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he was an old fox.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what he was.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a nice fellow.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was tough to get money out of, but I guess it was because they didn't have an awful lot operating there in Washington all those years, and they didn't draw an awful lot of people.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, the only year they ever, in the history of the ball club, the only year they drew over a million people was in 1946, the year after the war, when most of the ball clubs were drawing well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we used to draw like 400,000 a year.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I guess he couldn't afford to pay big salaries, but he was tough to get money out of.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was, every year,
[SPEAKER_00]: come contract time, you know, it was... All your negotiations would be with him?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: The letters from him personally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: He handled everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't have a general manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not many teams did, I guess, yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was certainly developing maybe about then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: He handled everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it wasn't like the owners of today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of the owners of today are fellows that go into baseball as a hobby or a sideline or a tax deduction or something or other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not Mr. Griffith and Mr. Mack, you know, and Mr. Yawkey and a few others.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were in baseball because it was their livelihood and it was their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: I always got the idea that Clark Griffith was a gentle, kind, old man.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in studying early baseball history, he was thrown out of more games for complaining about umpire decisions than up next to McGraw, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the worst actor.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you would get that impression if you met him in his later years that he was, like you say, and he hardly ever used any profanity.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I've read stories and talked to old-timers, you know, that we had on the ball club, like Clyde Milan, who was one of the coaches, and Bucky Harris, who played for Mr. Griffith.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they said he was the foulest-mouthed manager they'd ever played for, and the toughest.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, that's how he changed in his later years.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a nice man.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll tell you of an incident just to point out how thoughtful he was.
[SPEAKER_00]: My wife was pregnant.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'd been married about 11 years before we had our daughter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we were on our, not we, but the ball club was coming back from spring training by train.
[SPEAKER_00]: In those days, they'd play, you know, about a week to get north, they'd play teams
[SPEAKER_00]: on the way north in different cities and they traveled by train.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Mr. Griffith was coming up to Washington on the same train that my wife was coming up to Washington on, and he walked through about six or seven train cars looking for her so she could come back and eat with he and his wife so she wouldn't have to eat alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And here he was around 78, 80 years old at the time, and here he was walking through six, seven Pullman cars looking for her.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not many owners would do something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: How was Bucky Harris to play for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Bucky was great.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was good with young fellas and he, I think, a little different than some of the managers of today.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had a lot of patience
[SPEAKER_00]: and he would let you play your game and he would let you do things that if you did them you were hanging yourself more or less, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were doing something that you weren't supposed to be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then all of a sudden out of a clear sky he'd let you know that he knew it, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was playing first base in 39 when you came up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you share the job with them that year?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, at the beginning of the year, they had Jimmy Wazdell, and then they played Ozzie Bluejee, who was a third baseman most of his career.
[SPEAKER_00]: They played him there a couple of games and a couple of other fellas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were unsettled at first base when they brought me up in 1939.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then when I arrived, I played all the games the rest of the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: In 1940, when you were down in Jersey City, did Wasdell play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did they have somebody else that year?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they had gotten rid of Wasdell.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just can't recall who played in 1940.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I don't remember who played first base in 40.
[SPEAKER_01]: How were things at Jersey City that year?
[SPEAKER_01]: How did you like playing at Roosevelt State?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did they have big crowds there then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, they did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Opening day, the mayor, Mayor Haig, declares half a holiday on opening day when Jersey City would open, and he sold an awful lot of tickets.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had to announce attendance of 50-some thousand, but the place only held about 25, and it would be standing room only on opening day.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they'd always announce the big attendance to try to claim the highest attendance in baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was there a great rivalry between Newark and Georgia City?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there was quite a rivalry because it was so close.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can remember going over there in the bus and the kids stoning the bus as you're leaving the ballpark and hollering things at you, you know, like, hit the ramp, you're tramps, and get back up on that skyway and get back to Jersey City, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was all
[SPEAKER_00]: good competitive spirit, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where did you stay in Jersey City?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have rooming houses or hotels with a team?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you stay in New York?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when you're in your, what you call your base club home city, you are more or less on your own and you can live just about anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there were three of us that shared an apartment in downtown Jersey City right off of Journal Square.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who were they?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bob Sturgeon was one of them, a kid that later went up with the Cubs as a shortstop, and Wayne Ambler.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you remember Wayne Ambler?
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a second baseman with the A's.
[SPEAKER_00]: I lived with those fellows.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you went up in 1941, when did you learn you would stay with the team in 1941, in training?
[SPEAKER_01]: You had a pretty good year at Jersey City.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see, you had a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I had a fair year.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had about 280-something, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you probably had the job pretty well locked up, you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I don't think I did because they had drafted a first baseman from the Coast League by the name of George Archie, and he had just won the most valuable player award in the Coast League the year before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it looked like I was going to have to battle him for the job.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he opened the season at first base.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we were going to make our first Western trip.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Mr. Griffith called me over to the stands during batting practice one day at Griffith Stadium and said, you're going to
[SPEAKER_00]: leave the club in Chicago and we're going to send you up to Milwaukee in the American Association for the summer."
[SPEAKER_00]: And we had just rented an apartment over in Virginia and I told my wife to go see if she could get the rent back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so Steve Sundra, who was with us at the time, his wife went with her and they went over there and got it back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so we left that night on the train, went on our western swing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as luck would have it, I pinch hit in, I think, Detroit or Cleveland, one of those places.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I got a base hit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I pinch hit and got a base hit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then pinch hit again somewhere before we got to Chicago and got another base hit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when we got to Chicago, I was in the lineup.
[SPEAKER_00]: the first day, and I thought, you know, I would be leaving any day as soon as we got to Chicago to go to Milwaukee.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I played and got a couple hits, and I played from then on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And George Archie, the fellow that they had playing there— He went to Milwaukee.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: They put him at third base, and he played quite a few games at third base the rest of the year, and I played first.
[SPEAKER_01]: They didn't tell you, though, the Milwaukee trip was off.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just kept playing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and I didn't bother to ask him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't say, when am I going to Milwaukee?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did you feel in 1946 when you were leading the league in batting and getting no attention at all?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that cartoon on the front page of the Sporting News showing all the front page publicity to Williams, and there's a little note on the page, you're still leading the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the way I felt about it,
[SPEAKER_00]: At the time, I wasn't the type of player that got an awful lot of publicity anyway, and that didn't bother me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I kind of felt that they thought that eventually I was going to go into a slump or a tailspin and Williams was going to take over anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the way I thought that they were thinking, and therefore they weren't giving me an awful lot of publicity about leading the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: But maybe it was good that they didn't because it took some of the pressure off of me and I didn't have to think about it too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, I thought about it because I was, you know, right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a couple times Williams did catch me and one particular time he went ahead of me right, oh, three or four weeks before the season ended.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then I got hot again and ended up a few points ahead of him, about 11 or 12 points.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you feel a lot of pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or don't you feel pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I thought about it, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, you get keyed up and in that kind of a situation where you're battling for the batting championship, I think I stayed keyed up just about the last half of the season.
[SPEAKER_00]: An interesting story there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I think points out what I just said about, I didn't think that, I think that they thought I was going to, you know, probably not end up hitting, leading the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the all-star game 1946 in Boston, I was leading the league at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, and Bob Feller was contacting players to go on a barnstorming trip at the end of the season with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, and I was one of the ones that he wanted to take on the trip.
[SPEAKER_00]: And during our talk about what he was going to pay, he volunteered to pay me a bonus if I led the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't have to ask him for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had already told me what he was going to pay the players and what he was going to pay me for each game.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we were going to barnstorm for 30 days after the season was over.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, I'll give you X number of dollars as a bonus if you lead the league.
[SPEAKER_00]: And right then I'm thinking, you know, he doesn't think I'm going to lead the Laker, he wouldn't be offering me this money.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is why I think a lot of the people, mostly the writers, didn't think that here I am just coming back out of the service.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody had just got back, you know, all the ballplayers had just returned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And here I am, a fellow that hit 260 or 270 in 43 before I went into the service.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now here I am contending for the batting championship, and they think, well, he has never hit this high before, so maybe he won't hit this high right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Had Williams ever talked to you about this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I've talked to Williams about hitting and different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, during the season or?
[SPEAKER_00]: We were friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he didn't
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially talk about you think you're gonna lead the league, you know, when do you think you're gonna fold and that kind of stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no To to me and to most all the ballplayers that have ever played against him or with him Think Ted is one of the real fine guys in baseball.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know the writers had a lot of trouble with him and but I don't know of a ballplayer that
[SPEAKER_00]: unless it's a ball player that played under him as a manager, but I know, speaking as a player, that Ted had outstanding relationships with all the players.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did he always give his all out on the field there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or did he just look like he wasn't sometimes?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there were times when Ted gave the fans the impression that he didn't care, but
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think this ever happened when he walked up to the plate.
[SPEAKER_00]: He may have gave this impression when he was out in the field, but I don't think Ted ever walked to the plate without trying to get a base hit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tell that story you told me before about the 1953 batting race and how they were trying to, you told me the story about Elmer Vail on the field there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes you involved and you wouldn't catch one or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that was the last day, I think, the Valo incident.
[SPEAKER_00]: Last day of the season in Washington, Griffith Stadium.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd been leading the league most of the year and Rosen was having an outstanding year for Cleveland.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was coming on strong the last month of the season.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I honestly believe if the season had three or four more days to go, he would have taken over the batting championship.
[SPEAKER_00]: He led the league in home runs and runs batted in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was struggling to get that because it would have given him the triple crown.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was getting two, three, four hits a game coming down the stretch, but he just
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, a lot of people say I beat him out by a point or a percentage point or something, but actually he didn't catch me.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, uh, the last day of the season, I think he got three hits and, and one, uh, and we were in constant, uh, contact with the game in Cleveland.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, uh, and we knew what he was doing each time at bat and I was playing in Washington, but our.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our announcer, Arch McDonald, had an open phone with the press box in Cleveland, and he would relay to us on the bench what Rosen was doing each time at bat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think he had a fourth hit, but he got called out at first base because he didn't touch first base.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had stepped over the bag, and Hank Sauer was the umpire and called him out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I had a couple hits, and the
[SPEAKER_00]: The incident with Vallow, I hit a ball over the fence about a yard foul and then I hit a line shot that Vallow almost staggered underneath and he just dug up his hand and caught it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he told me later, he said, I tried my best to misjudge it, he said, but it would have looked too bad, he said, I had to catch it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wanted you to win that batting title.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, the players on the Washington Club, on account of the constant report from the press box, they figured they would try to keep me from going to bat an extra time.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it looked like I was going to need another time at bat and I might need a hit to beat him out, they tried to get out.
[SPEAKER_00]: so I wouldn't have to come to bat.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget who it was, I think it was Eddie Yost hit a double and got thrown out at the second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another fellow hit a single and kept on going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Yost hit the double and got the second and got picked off a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the other fellow I think was a fellow named Thomas, an outfielder.
[SPEAKER_00]: He hit a single and got thrown out at second.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the way it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I did manage to come to bat.
[SPEAKER_01]: When did you know that you had won it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right after the game?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, after the game they figured it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did you feel about all that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Were you under any pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you feel a lot of pressure this time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's remarkable, two batting championships.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were never injured, were you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seriously.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had a broken rib.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tommy Byrne hit me about five times one year and the last week of the season we were going to New York and to Boston to finish the season and while in New York he hit me in the rib and cracked one of my ribs and then I had a couple sprained ankles but this is the most serious.
[SPEAKER_00]: I never had a lot of pulled muscles.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you account for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess on account of the way I was built, I was lean and skinny, you know, and wasn't muscular like, you know, when a fellow's real developed and muscular, he gets a lot of pulled muscles.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it was mainly on account of the way I was built.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you ever get thrown out of any games?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I was thrown out two while I played, and I don't know the count while I was managing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I got thrown out a few times while I was managing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The two times I was thrown out while I was playing was George Pipgrass, the old Yankee pitcher that later became an umpire.
[SPEAKER_00]: He threw me out in Boston one day for complaining about a third called strike.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think he threw me out so much on account of that, but I think he threw me out because I made a remark to him that
[SPEAKER_00]: recalled something that he didn't like and it was something that Bucky had said to him the year before and was thrown out of the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said to him, I said, you know what Bucky told you last year, well that goes for me too.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the other time was Ed Runge threw me out in Kansas City one time for complaining about a play at first base.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had this reputation of being Somali, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about any fights?
[SPEAKER_01]: I understood you slugged Jerry Pretty once, is that true?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, he was a teammate.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was playing second base on the Washington club and we'd just lost a ball game in Detroit and we come in the clubhouse and a few words went, you know, first thing you know we're swinging at each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's been in the news of late, hasn't he?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sorry to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about your relations with the press?
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't say bad relations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have any particular relations?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you know many of the writers?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't think of anything to report here.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only
[SPEAKER_00]: time that I really got a lot of publicity that was unfavorable, I guess, was the last year I managed in Washington when a couple of the papers there, particularly the little tabloid, they were giving me a little rough time then.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this happens to a lot of managers that are getting ready to get the axe, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: As a player, though, you had pretty good relationships.
[SPEAKER_01]: About Shirley Povich, did you know him?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, Shirley was a veteran when I broke in.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see where he's just retiring.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shirley at times would take a rap at you, but you can't get good write-ups all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then a fellow by the name of Bert Hawkins that wrote for the Evening Star and later became the traveling secretary for the club when they had the expansion and I became the manager and he was my traveling secretary.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he didn't always give all the fellows the best of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once in a while he would take a rap at us.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is their job and if you're not doing a good job on the field, they should report it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a very fair attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about your favorite ballpark?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, Detroit and New York.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that League Park in Cleveland?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, League Park, yes, I played in League Park.
[SPEAKER_00]: I hit my first major league home run there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I only played there a few years and then they moved to downtown, the big ballpark.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, at one time,
[SPEAKER_00]: We'd play, if we happened to be scheduled in Cleveland on a weekend, we'd play Friday maybe in League Park and then Saturday, or play Friday night down at the Big Ball Park and Saturday afternoon in League Park and then Sunday back at the Big Park.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then eventually they moved all the games to the Big Park.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I can remember, you know, switching back and forth to League Stadium and Municipal Stadium.
[SPEAKER_01]: You like Detroit?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, being a hitter, you kind of favor the parks that you think you've done best in, and Detroit was one of my favorite hitting parks, and New York.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, of course I played all my home games there, but I liked Griffith Stadium for this reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was kind of a spray hitter, and they had a large left field.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this way I got a lot of base hits in the left field that maybe I wouldn't get in Boston, you know, where they had a short left field.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you think if you'd been in Yankee Stadium your home or outfield would have been a little better?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or Detroit.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about some exciting plays?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any unusual plays?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I can't think of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any 1-6-1 double plays or unassisted double plays of note?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the only play that I can think of would be the first triple play that I was in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mike Higgins was the hitter for Detroit, and I thought he was going to
[SPEAKER_00]: and I was playing in and he hit a line shot right at me and I run over and stepped on first base and threw to second base for the triple play.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have any, were you frequently able to make the play to third base on bunts, attempted sacrifices?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I made that play a few times, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ferris Fane used to make it quite often.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was pretty good at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was quick and he had a good arm and he could come over and
[SPEAKER_00]: field the ball on the third-base side and make the play to third, which is unusual for a first baseman.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't get over there that quick.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I recall seeing him once in Cleveland on his hands and knees along the third-base line where he went into field, but he was going to roll foul, so he just let it go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think he even blew it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I asked you once about your most difficult play.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe that was that one-six or that double play that
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're holding a man on first base, it's not too difficult because you don't have far to get back.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're playing with a man on first and second and you're playing back fairly deep and you have to go to second and then to first, it's a little tougher because you have to move pretty quick after you've thrown the ball to second and you also have to look for the bag and then also look for the throw coming back at you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's a little rougher than if you're holding just a man on first base.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one of the toughest plays for a first baseman is making up his mind whether to go for that slow hit ground ball or let the second baseman field it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see this happen a lot because the first baseman is undecided whether to let it go or to break for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll break for a lot of balls that he shouldn't and you'll see the second baseman call him off and
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the pitcher has to come over and cover the bag.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he may be a little late getting there because he thought the first baseman was going to cover the first base anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this, I think, is a tough play for a first baseman, making up his mind to go for that ball or go for the bag.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your biggest thrill?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, my top thrill would have to be leading the league in hitting first time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I also have to rate an opening day thrill that
[SPEAKER_00]: I had in 1954 when I hit a home run against the Yankees to win the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allie Reynolds had come in to relieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: After I circled the bases, a Secret Service man grabbed me and took me over to President Eisenhower's box to be congratulated by him, and the photographers were there.
[SPEAKER_00]: After I had dressed, they rushed me out to Old Forest Park.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not Forest Park, but oh, I can't even think of the hotel's name where Cameron Swayze was doing his news broadcast and I went on the show with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this was an exciting day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Jay, I could go on here for some time, but how about one more, the toughest pitcher?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bob Feller.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bob Feller, without a doubt, he was the toughest for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had a lot of tough ones, but if I have to pinpoint one, it would be Bob Feller.